A Guide to the Henry L. Gray Letters, 1863-1886
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Henry L. Gray Letters, 1863-1886 (Bulk, 1863-1865)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2001-002
0.2 cu. ft. 1 box
The collection includes correspondence by Henry L. Gray, written primarily between 1863-1865. There are also some official documents from Gray's military activities.
Grey, Henry L.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Henry L. Gray Letters were purchased by Special Collections in 2001.
Biographical Note
Henry L. Gray was a Union soldier enlisted as a private from 1863-1865 in the 14th Maine volunteer infantry Company G. His family lived in Bradley, Penobscot County, Maine. Gray served on the USS Cambridge and traveled to a variety of Union camps including Gosport Navy Yard in Virginia, Beaufort, North Carolina, Camp Coburn in Augusta, Maine, Boston Harbor, and Savannah, Georgia. For further information on the involvement of the 14th Maine infantry in the Civil War reference the National Park Service Civil War database.
Source: National Park Service, Henry L. Gray
Scope and Content
This collection contains letters to Henry L. Gray's family in Bradley, Maine chronicling his time with the USS Cambridge and their activities throughout the Civil War. Included in the correspondence are notes on the locations of the ship, proximity to rebel forces, capture of Charleston by the Union Army, and the rebel blockade in Savannah, Georgia. He also references such historical events as the death of Lincoln and the surrenders of General Lee and General Wheeler as well as a first-hand account of the capture of Confederate President Jefferson Davis and the Confederate Vice President. Gray documents where Davis and the Vice President were sent after their capture and how he was a member of their escort to Washington, D.C in 1865. Along with these historical events, Gray documents eating habits of soldiers, process of requesting furlough, and general life of a soldier during the Civil War from 1863-1865. Included in the collection are Henry Gray's proof of enlistment and request of a pension from the Department of the Interior and Surgeon General as well as a letter from his brother to the pension office explaining Henry's suspension from duty due to an injury.
Arrangement
The correspondence is arranged chronologically with Henry L. Gray's proof of enlistment and personal documents at the end.
Index Terms
Persons:
Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865
Subjects:
Civil War; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents List
- December 1, 1863 (Box-folder 1-1)
- January 4, 1964 (Box-folder 1-2)
- [Gosport Navy Yard] (Box-folder 1-3)
- June 25, 1864 (Box-folder 1-4)
- July 2, 1864 (Box-folder 1-5)
- July 8, 1864 (Box-folder 1-6)
- July 19, 1864 (Box-folder 1-7)
- July 27, 1864 (Box-folder 1-8)
- September 13, 1864 (Box-folder 1-9)
- October 13, 1864 (Box-folder 1-10)
- March 3, 1865 (Box-folder 1-11)
- [Camp Coburn] (Box-folder 1-12)
- March 16, 1865 (Box-folder 1-13)
- March 24, 1865 (Box-folder 1-14)
- March 31, 1865 (Box-folder 1-15)
- April 11, 1865 (Box-folder 1-16)
- April 19, 1865 (Box-folder 1-17)
- May 1, 1865 (Box-folder 1-18)
- June 25, 1865 (Box-folder 1-19)
- July 25, 1865 (Box-folder 1-20)
- Official documents (Box-folder 1-21)